<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Latest News | Doyle Group</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/en/post/</link><atom:link href="https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/en/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Latest News</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/media/logo_hu_f4e82b191d2fa997.png</url><title>Latest News</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/en/post/</link></image><item><title>Vibrational branching fractions for laser cooling of Sr-containing nonlinear molecules</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/en/post/2024-08-01-featured-pra/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/en/post/2024-08-01-featured-pra/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/pra/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevA.110.022811" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Paper&lt;/a> by Alex and Zack (with collaborator Lan Cheng) has been featured in Editor&amp;rsquo;s Suggestion on PRA.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The authors explore candidates for a next-generation search for the electron electric dipole moment (eEDM) by experimentally measuring the vibrational loss channels in three Sr-containing nonlinear molecules. They conclude that SrNH2 is the optimal choice for a future laser-cooled molecule-based eEDM experiment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The vibrational branching fractions from the lowest excited electronic state for SrOCH3, SrNH2, and SrSH are measured at the &amp;lt;0.1% level. Spectra are obtained by driving the X̃−Ã transitions and dispersing the fluorescence on a grating spectrometer. We also perform ab initio calculations for the energies of vibrational levels relevant for laser cooling, as well as branching fractions to support the interpretations of all molecular spectra. Symmetry-group analysis is applied in conjunction with our data to study rotational closure in these molecules. These analyses indicate favorable prospects for laser cooling SrNH2 and other similar alkaline-earth-metal(-like) amides for future beyond the Standard Model physics searches using polyatomic molecules with long-lived parity doublets.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Individual polyatomic molecules are trapped in optical tweezer arrays</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/en/post/2024-04-01-caoh-tweezers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/en/post/2024-04-01-caoh-tweezers/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our results on an &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07199-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">optical tweezer array of ultracold polyatomic molecules demonstrate control of polyatomic molecules&lt;/a> (CaOH) at the single particle, single internal quantum state level. The ability to create and manipulate tweezer arrays of polyatomic molecules paves the way for a variety of experiments harnessing the rich structure of these molecules, including quantum simulation, quantum computation, and precision studies of ultracold collisions and chemistry. Check out popular news coverage of this work in &lt;a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/individual-polyatomic-molecules-are-trapped-in-optical-tweezer-arrays/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Physics World&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2024-05-physicists-optical-tweezer-array-individual.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Phys.org&lt;/a>. Also see the &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-01009-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nature Research Briefing&lt;/a> on this article.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>