<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research | Doyle Group</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/</link><atom:link href="https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Research</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/media/logo_hu_f4e82b191d2fa997.png</url><title>Research</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/</link></image><item><title>CaF - Quantum Simulation and Information with Diatomic Molecules</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/caf/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/caf/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the CaF laser cooling experiment, we seek to study ultracold molecules by first loading molecules into a magneto-optical trap (MOT) and then transferring these molecules to an optical trap for further cooling. Interesting later experiments could involve studying atom-molecule or molecule-molecule collisions, as well as using the ultracold sample of diatomic molecules for quantum simulation and quantum computation, or a path finder for precision measurement experiments.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="loading-molecules">Loading Molecules&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The first step of this experiment is to load a magneto-optical trap (MOT) with the diatomic radical calcium monofluoride (CaF) using a buffer-gas beam source (for details on buffer-gas cells see [1-3]). We first ablate a solid precursor of atomic Ca with a pulsed Nd:YAG laser. We simultaneously flow sulfur hexafluoride (SF6) into the buffer-gas cell, leading to a chemical reaction which produces CaF. The hot molecular gas then thermalizes with ~1 K Helium buffer-gas and is extracted into a beam. The molecular beam has an average forward velocity of 50-60 m/s out of our two-stage cell. While such velocities are low enough to load conventional atomic MOTs (see our previous work on lanthanide atoms), the estimated capture velocity for a MOT of CaF is less than 10 m/s. A slowing stage is thus required to bring a sufficient number of molecules to below the capture velocity. We use a slowing technique for this beam deceleration, as was demonstrated in our recent paper [14]. An additional challenge to trapping molecules is the existence of magnetic dark states in molecules, which arise due to the fact that we trap the molecules on a transition with &amp;ldquo;inverted&amp;rdquo; angular momentum structure. We address this problem by switching the polarization and the magnetic field of the MOT very rapidly (~1 MHz) to depopulate those dark states (so called RF MOT). Finally, over a million molecules are loaded into the MOT.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="CaF MOT Chamber" srcset="
/doyle-group-site/media/caf/caf_mot_chamber_hu_f8d535fdbc0bb135.webp 400w,
/doyle-group-site/media/caf/caf_mot_chamber_hu_cd17b5a51a2d08b9.webp 760w,
/doyle-group-site/media/caf/caf_mot_chamber_hu_7f9ad643cda28e3f.webp 1200w"
src="https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/media/caf/caf_mot_chamber_hu_f8d535fdbc0bb135.webp"
width="753"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>b&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ACME - Precision Measurement of the Electron Electric Dipole Moment (EDM)</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/acme/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/acme/</guid><description>&lt;p>The ACME experiment uses a cryogenic molecular beam of the heavy polar molecule ThO to measure the electron&amp;rsquo;s electric dipole moment (EDM). The existence of an electron EDM would manifest itself as very small energy shifts in certain molecular states when the molecules are in an electric field. The electron EDM is a strong probe of physics beyond the Standard Model.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The molecular beam is created by buffer gas cooling an ablated sample of ThO, which then flows out of an orifice. The molecules enter a magnetically shielded vacuum chamber that contains uniform electric and magnetic fields. We optically pump the molecules into the &amp;ldquo;H&amp;rdquo; electronic (EDM sensitive) state, and then polarize them by optically pumping undesired polarizations out of the H state. The molecules then precess in the fields, and we read out the accumulated phase with polarized lasers. By reversing the electric field, we can reverse the amount of precession accumulated from the electron EDM; taking the difference between these two phases yields the electron EDM.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This idea is the basis for any permanent EDM search, whether it is for atoms, neutrons, or electrons, however our experiment has several features that enhance our sensitivity:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Polar Molecule. Polar molecules have the highest known sensitivity to an electron electric dipole moment. The electric field inside a polar molecule can be as large as tens of gigavolts per centimeter, almost a million times larger than any controlled field that can be created in a laboratory. Because the energy of a dipole moment in an electric field is proportional to the field strength, the electrons orbiting a polar molecule can experience these large fields and give proportionally larger energy shift. The electric field in ThO has been calculated to be 84 GV/cm, one of the largest known.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Internal Co-magnetometer&lt;/strong>. Since we measure tiny energy splittings, a small stray electric or magnetic field can could destroy our signal. Even worse, these stray fields could look like an EDM in certain situations, for example from leakage currents between the electric field plates. Our molecule has a parity doublet: two close-lying (a few hundred kilohertz in zero field) states of opposite parity in the ground rotational level of the H state. In addition to allowing complete polarization of the molecule in very weak fields, the two components of this doublet have equal yet opposite shifts from an electron EDM. In other words, the two different doublet states correspond to spectroscopically reversing the internal electric field experienced by the electron. Therefore, we can perform our field reversal without reversing any external fields, which will give us very powerful rejection of systematic errors. Other limiting systematics, such as geometric phases, can also be eliminated because they do not reverse between populating the different doublets.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Cryogenic Beam Source&lt;/strong>. Our hydrodynamically-enhanced buffer gas cooled beam is high flux, cold, and slow. We produce beams of ThO with time-averaged fluxes of over 10^13 molecules/state/sr/second moving with a forward velocity of 170 m/s, without the need for stark or optical deceleration.``&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>CaNH₂ - Cooling Asymmetric Molecules</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/canh2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/canh2/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="laser-cooling-the-force-awakens">Laser Cooling: The Force Awakens&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Since its invention in the 1980s, laser-cooling technology has evolved into a cornerstone of AMO physics. By enabling the production of ultracold, dense atomic ensembles, researchers have ventured into the realm of quantum degeneracy, and achieved control over individual quantum states using optical tweezers and lattices. These breakthroughs have catalyzed significant advances in quantum computing [1-3], quantum simulation [4-7], atomic clocks [8], and precision tests of fundamental constants [9].&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-ultracold-molecule-chronicles">The Ultracold Molecule Chronicles&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Building on decades of success in atomic physics, recent research has turned to ultracold molecules as powerful tools for exploring new quantum phenomena. Experimental efforts worldwide, including those in our group, are extending the laser-cooling toolkit into the rich and intricate world of molecules. Over the past decade, laser cooling has been demonstrated in diatomic species (e.g., CaF [20-22], SrF [13], YO [14]), linear triatomic molecules (e.g., CaOH [15], SrOH [16]), and even larger symmetric top molecules (e.g., &lt;a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abc5357" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CaOCH&lt;sub>3&lt;/sub>&lt;/a> [17]). Yet our ambitions push us further, towards a more complex molecular landscape.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="taming-the-untamed-cooling-asymmetric-molecules">Taming the Untamed: Cooling Asymmetric Molecules&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our latest project, launched in late 2024, takes on a new challenge: adapting established laser-cooling techniques to more complex, asymmetric top molecules. Drawing on theoretical insights from previous studies [19,20], we aim to demonstrate that even large, bent, and twisted molecules can be controlled with laser light. For this experiment, we have chosen CaNH&lt;sub>2&lt;/sub>—the simplest asymmetric top molecule—to test our cooling strategies and pave the way for broader applications in quantum science.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[1] D. Bluvstein, S. J. Evered, A. A. Geim, S. H. Li, H. Zhou, T. Manovitz, S. Ebadi, M. Cain, M. Kalinowski, D. Hangleiter, et al., “Logical quantum processor based on reconfigurable atom arrays,” Nature, vol. 626, no. 7997, pp. 58–65, 2024.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] I. S. Madjarov, J. P. Covey, A. L. Shaw, J. Choi, A. Kale, A. Cooper, H. Pichler, V. Schkolnik, J. R. Williams, and M. Endres, “High-fidelity entanglement and detection of alkaline-earth rydberg atoms,” Nature Physics, vol. 16, no. 8, pp. 857–861, 2020.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[3] L. Isenhower, E. Urban, X. Zhang, A. Gill, T. Henage, T. A. Johnson, T. Walker, and M. Saffman, “Demonstration of a neutral atom controlled-not quantum gate,” Physical Review Letters, vol. 104, no. 1, p. 010503, 2010.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[4] H. Labuhn, D. Barredo, S. Ravets, S. De L´es´eleuc, T. Macr`ı, T. Lahaye, and A. Browaeys, “Tunable two-dimensional arrays of single rydberg atoms for realizing quantum ising models,” Nature, vol. 534, no. 7609, pp. 667–670, 2016.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[5] H. Bernien, S. Schwartz, A. Keesling, H. Levine, A. Omran, H. Pichler, S. Choi, A. S. Zibrov, M. Endres, M. Greiner, et al., “Probing many-body dynamics on a 51-atom quantum simulator,” Nature, vol. 551, no. 7682, pp. 579–584, 2017.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[6] W. S. Bakr, J. I. Gillen, A. Peng, S. F¨olling, and M. Greiner, “A quantum gas microscope for detecting single atoms in a hubbard-regime optical lattice,” Nature, vol. 462, no. 7269, pp. 74–77, 2009.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[7] M. F. Parsons, A. Mazurenko, C. S. Chiu, G. Ji, D. Greif, and M. Greiner, “Site-resolved measurement of the spin-correlation function in the fermi-hubbard model,” Science, vol. 353, no. 6305, pp. 1253–1256, 2016.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[8] Hinkley, N., Sherman, J. A., Phillips, N. B., Schioppo, M., Lemke, N. D., Beloy, K., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Ludlow, A. D. (2013). An atomic clock with 10–18 instability. Science, 341(6151), 1215-1218.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[9] T. Bothwell, C. J. Kennedy, A. Aeppli, D. Kedar, J. M. Robinson, E. Oelker, A. Staron, and J. Ye, “Resolving the gravitational redshift across a millimetre-scale atomic sample,” Nature, vol. 602, no. 7897, pp. 420–424, 2022.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[10] L. Anderegg, B. L. Augenbraun, E. Chae, B. Hemmerling, N. R. Hutzler, A. Ravi, A. Collopy, J. Ye, W. Ketterle, and J. M. Doyle, “Radio frequency magneto-optical trapping of caf with high density,” Physical Review Letters, vol. 119, no. 10, p. 103201, 2017.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[11] S. Truppe, H. Williams, M. Hambach, L. Caldwell, N. Fitch, E. Hinds, B. Sauer, and M. Tarbutt, “Molecules cooled below the doppler limit,” Nature Physics, vol. 13, no. 12, pp. 1173–1176, 2017.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[12] S. J. Li, C. M. Holland, Y. Lu, and L. W. Cheuk, “Blue-detuned magneto-optical trap of caf molecules,” Physical Review Letters, vol. 132, no. 23, p. 233402, 2024.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[13]J. Barry, D. McCarron, E. Norrgard, M. Steinecker, and D. DeMille, “Magneto-optical trapping of a diatomic molecule,” Nature, vol. 512, no. 7514, pp. 286–289, 2014.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[14] A. L. Collopy, S. Ding, Y. Wu, I. A. Finneran, L. Anderegg, B. L. Augenbraun, J. M. Doyle, and J. Ye, “3d magneto-optical trap of yttrium monoxide,” Physical Review Letters, vol. 121, no. 21, p. 213201, 2018.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[15 ]N. B. Vilas, C. Hallas, L. Anderegg, P. Robichaud, A. Winnicki, D. Mitra, and J. M. Doyle, “Magneto-optical trapping and sub-doppler cooling of a polyatomic molecule,” Nature, vol. 606, no. 7912, pp. 70–74, 2022.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[16] Z. D. Lasner, A. Frenett, H. Sawaoka, L. Anderegg, B. Augenbraun, H. Lampson, M. Li, A. Lunstad, J. Mango, A. Nasir, et al., “Magneto-optical trapping of a heavy polyatomic molecule for precision measurement,” arXiv preprint arXiv:2409.04948, 2024.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[17] Mitra, Debayan, et al. &amp;ldquo;Direct laser cooling of a symmetric top molecule.&amp;rdquo; Science 369.6509 (2020): 1366-1369.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[19] Kozyryev, Baum, Matsuda, and Doyle, &amp;ldquo;Proposal for Laser Cooling of Complex Polyatomic Molecules,&amp;rdquo; ChemPhysChem 17(22), 3641-3648 (2016).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[20] Augenbraun, Doyle, Zelevinsky, and Kozyryev, &amp;ldquo;Molecular Asymmetry and Optical Cycling: Laser Cooling Asymmetric Top Molecules,&amp;rdquo; Phys. Rev. X 10, 031022 (2020).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CaOH</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/caoh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/caoh/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="research-overview">Research Overview&lt;/h1>
&lt;div style="float: right; margin: 0 0 10px 10px; text-align: center; width: 250px;">
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Linear Triatomic Molecule" srcset="
/doyle-group-site/media/caoh/645px-sroh_straight_at_angle_hu_96193d830ff0ae02.webp 400w,
/doyle-group-site/media/caoh/645px-sroh_straight_at_angle_hu_2b7774df35e0dabb.webp 760w,
/doyle-group-site/media/caoh/645px-sroh_straight_at_angle_hu_d23d92d770d32883.webp 1200w"
src="https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/media/caoh/645px-sroh_straight_at_angle_hu_96193d830ff0ae02.webp"
width="645"
height="599"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The goal of this experiment is to bring polyatomic molecules into the ultracold regime using direct laser cooling. The use of laser radiation to control and cool external and internal degrees of freedom has revolutionized atomic, molecular, and optical physics [1]. The powerful techniques of laser cooling and trapping using light scattering forces for atoms led to breakthroughs in both fundamental and applied sciences, including detailed studies of degenerate quantum gases and many-body physics [2,3], creation of novel frequency standards [4], and precision measurements of fundamental constants [5,6]. Polyatomic molecules are more difficult to manipulate than atoms and diatomic molecules because they possess additional rotational and vibrational degrees of freedom. Partially because of their increased complexity, cold dense samples of molecules with three or more atoms offer unique capabilities for exploring interdisciplinary frontiers in physics, chemistry and even biology. Precise control over polyatomic molecules could lead to applications in astrophysics [7], quantum simulation [8] and computation [9,10], fundamental physics [11,12], and chemistry [13]. Study of parity violation in biomolecular chirality [14]—which plays a fundamental role in molecular biology [15]—necessarily requires polyatomic molecules.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Motivated by recent successes in the laser cooling and trapping of diatomic molecules [16-20], as well as recent demonstrations in our group of laser cooling of triatomic molecules [21-24], we are currently working to load a magneto-optical trap (MOT) with the linear, triatomic molecule calcium monohydroxide (CaOH). Our approach starts with buffer gas cooling [25-27], a technique that dramatically reduces the number of populated internal rotational and vibrational states by thermalizing a sample of molecules with helium gas at ~2K. This initial cooling step is critical for working with molecules to limit the number of quantum states that have significant population, and our two-stage buffer gas cell design has additionally allowed us to produce a slow beam of CaOH molecules with a peak velocity below 100 m/s. We are now working to adapt successful atomic and diatomic laser cooling techniques to triatomic CaOH. We have recently demonstrated 1D cooling and compression of the molecular beam using a one-dimensional MOT [28]; this has allowed us to demonstrate the feasibility of scattering thousands of photons via radiative cooling and the application of magneto-optical forces, both of which will be necessary for 3D trapping. We will next radiatively slow the CaOH beam, which can be accomplished using a white-light slowing scheme [29]. We will then produce a 3D MOT using techniques similar to those demonstrated with diatomic SrF and CaF [16-18]. Unlike electronic and rotational transitions, there are no selection rules governing vibrational degrees of freedom in molecules, forcing us to rely on molecule-dependent vibrational branching ratios to avoid decay out of the cooling cycle. These have been shown to be favorable in CaOH [30], meaning that direct laser cooling and slowing should be feasible with a manageable number of repumping lasers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are additionally examining how to extend laser cooling techniques to more complex polyatomic molecules, such as symmetric tops like CaOCH3, and have identified a number of large polyatomics expected to have near-diagonal Franck-Condon factors [30, 31].&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>RaX - Radium Molecules for BSM Physics</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/rax/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/rax/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are building a new experiment to laser cool radium-containing molecules, in collaboration with &lt;a href="https://www.garciaruizlab.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MIT (Garcia Ruiz group)&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.hutzlerlab.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Caltech (Hutzler group)&lt;/a>, and the &lt;a href="https://frib.msu.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Facility for Rare Isotope Beams (FRIB)&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-radium">Why Radium?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Radium-containing molecules offer unparalleled opportunity to study some of the open questions in our understanding of the universe, such as the root cause of the observed matter/antimatter asymmetry, the long-sought search for CP violation in the strong interaction, and the potential existence of yet-undetected particles and forces [1, 2, 3]. The octuple deformation of radium nuclei [4] is predicted to amplify both parity (P) and time-reversal (T) violating nuclear properties by more than three orders of magnitude compared to stable molecules [5, 6, 7].&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recent results in the spectroscopy of radioactive molecules have demonstrated that radium-containing molecules, such as 225RaF and 225RaOH, additionally possess a relatively simple structure that is very favorable for laser cooling (see Fig. 1) [7, 8, 9]. This combination makes these molecules excellent quantum sensors for fundamental physics, opening the door to searches for P,T violating nuclear effects, such as the nuclear Schiff moment, manifesting as electric dipole moments (EDMs) of molecules [1, 2, 3].&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="experimental-work">Experimental Work&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The roadmap to ultra-sensitive measurements with radium-containing molecules begins with the less radioactive isotope 226Ra (τ1/2 = 1600 yr), simplifying the experimental apparatus and molecule structure, and enabling rapid prototyping at university laboratories. To demonstrate the first laser cooling and trapping of a radioactive molecule, we will work with the well-characterized diatomic molecule 226RaF, which has an ideal molecular structure for laser cooling [9]. Concurrently, we will also test optical cycling (the key property that enables laser cooling) in 226RaOH, where the polyatomic structure generically provides parity doublets, a powerful structural advantage for state-of-the-art precision measurements [10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15]. Fortunately, RaF and RaOH molecules have isoelectronic structure; hence sharing common production methods and similar optical transitions, accessible with common laser technologies. Many of the initial experimental breakthroughs in RaF can pave the way for advances with RaOH, and their similarity enables changing from RaF to RaOH in an experiment with the metaphorical “flip of a switch”.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="RaF Franck-Condon Factors" srcset="
/doyle-group-site/media/rax/raf_cooling_hu_462024b00bc442f4.webp 400w,
/doyle-group-site/media/rax/raf_cooling_hu_120eea432f0fab14.webp 760w,
/doyle-group-site/media/rax/raf_cooling_hu_19819e511212b421.webp 1200w"
src="https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/media/rax/raf_cooling_hu_462024b00bc442f4.webp"
width="572"
height="720"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Initially, experimental prototyping will be performed in cold (∼ K) molecular beams, an essential tool for measuring, cooling, and trapping molecules. This experiment will overcome challenges in producing and cooling 226Ra-containing molecules, establishing the path for future work to capture the molecular beam in a long-lived trap at ultracold temperatures (&amp;lt; mK). This work will establish the experimental basis for eventual enhanced hadronic symmetry violation measurements with 225Ra (τ1/2 = 14.9 d) containing molecules at the Facility for Rare Isotope Beams (FRIB).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[1] W. B. Cairncross, J. Ye, Nature Reviews Physics 1, 510–521 (Aug. 2019).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] R. Alarcon et al., Electric dipole moments and the search for new physics, 2022.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[3] G. Arrowsmith-Kron et al., arXiv preprint arXiv:2302.02165 (2023).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[4] Gaffney, L. P. et al., Nature 497, 199–204 (May 2013).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[5] V. Spevak, N. Auerbach, V. V. Flambaum, Physical Review C - Nuclear Physics 56, 1357–1369, arXiv: 9612044 (nucl-th) (1997).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[6] J. Dobaczewski, J. Engel, M. Kortelainen, P. Becker, Physical Review Letters 121, 232501 (23 Dec. 2018).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[7] R. F. Garcia Ruiz et al., Nature 581, 396–400 (May 2020).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[8] S. M. Udrescu et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 127, 033001 (3 July 2021).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[9] S. M. Udrescu et al., Nature Physics 20, 202–207 (Feb. 2024).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[10] I. Kozyryev, N. R. Hutzler. Phys. Rev. Lett. 119.13 (Sept. 2017).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[11] T. S. Roussy et al., Science 381, 46–50 (2023).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[12] V. Andreev et al., Nature 562, 355–360 (Oct. 2018).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[13] L. Anderegg et al., Science 382, 665–668 (Nov. 2023).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[14] Y. Takahashi, C. Zhang, A. Jadbabaie, N. R. Hutzler, Physical Review Letters 131, 183003 (Oct. 2023).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[15] C. Zhang, P. Yu, A. Jadbabaie, N. R. Hutzler, Physical Review Letters131, 193602 (Nov. 2023).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Searching for Ultralight Dark Matter - SrOH</title><link>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/sroh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/project/sroh/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="missing-matter">Missing matter&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The current framework of fundamental physics, called the Standard Model (SM), has successfully withstood every laboratory test. Furthermore, with the discovery of the Higgs particle in 2012, every core prediction of the SM has been validated by experiment. Despite these successes, the SM alone cannot explain the entirety of fundamental physics. Perhaps most dramatically, astronomical observations over the last fifty years have shown that only 15% of the matter in the universe is composed of particles described by the SM. The remaining particles, which do not (or only very weakly) interact with light, are known as &amp;ldquo;dark&amp;rdquo; matter. Very little is known with certainty about the nature of dark matter.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One major source of evidence for dark matter is gravitational lensing (see right), where the path of light from distant galaxies is bent by the gravitational in uence of galaxies in the cosmic neighborhood of its trajectory. As a result, images of the night sky become distorted. By analyzing the distortions, it is possible to infer the positions and masses of the gravitational sources. This method produces the most accurate maps of the matter density throughout the universe. Remarkably, these maps show that all visible matter comprises only a small fraction of all matter. The difference is &amp;ldquo;dark matter,&amp;rdquo; which is gravitationally active but does not emit or absorb light. Simulations of nucleosynthesis and cosmological structure formation as well as observations of the cosmic microwave background are also consistent with a universe composed of 85% dark matter [1].&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="polyatomic-molecules-as-dark-matter-sensors">Polyatomic molecules as dark matter sensors&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In many well-motivated models, cold dark matter particles behave collectively like a classical field throughout space (such as a gravitational field) [2]. Such a dark matter field would oscillate at a frequency determined by the mass of each particle. Depending on its interactions with ordinary matter, electrons and nuclei would undergo a slight change in mass that follows the oscillation of the dark matter field. Thus high-precision measurements of fundamental &amp;ldquo;constants,&amp;rdquo; such as the ratio of electron mass to prooton mass, could reveal a small time-dependence. The magnitude of this time-dependent part of the fundamental constant contains information about the interactions between dark matter and ordinary matter, while the frequency of oscillation would reveal the dark matter particle mass.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="energy-oscillation">Energy oscillation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The energies of molecular vibrations and rotations depend on the proton-to-electron mass ratio, denoted by μ: for example, increasing the proton mass (with the electron mass fixed) reduces the energy of a rotating or vibrating molecule. The fractional change in the energy of a rotating or vibrating molecule is typically the same (within a factor of two) as the fractional change in μ. However, absolute energies of individual states are not physically meaningful. Only energy differences can be measured. Certain special cases arise where the energies of two molecular states are nearly identical, but the states each have different fractional depenences on μ. In these cases, the dependence of the fractional energy difference on fractional changes in μ can be enhanced by a factor of hundreds to thousands! Oftentimes, experimental sensitivity is limited by systematic errors scaling with the absolute energy difference between two states (for example, due to technical noise sources in high-frequency radiation sources like lasers). Then, a larger fractional sensitivity of the transition can lead to a better ultimate absolute sensitivity to changes in μ.
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/doyle-group-site/media/sroh/energy-oscillation-diagram_hu_eaa07d78cc013456.webp 400w,
/doyle-group-site/media/sroh/energy-oscillation-diagram_hu_8088e19738f5782d.webp 760w,
/doyle-group-site/media/sroh/energy-oscillation-diagram_hu_75f520cf0d5f52f.webp 1200w"
src="https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/media/sroh/energy-oscillation-diagram_hu_eaa07d78cc013456.webp"
width="760"
height="428"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="laboratory-based-dark-matter-detection-with-laser-cooled-sroh">Laboratory-based dark matter detection with laser-cooled SrOH&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Bichromatic Force laser cooling of SrOH" srcset="
/doyle-group-site/media/sroh/coolingsroh_hu_a565ac579b4cf016.webp 400w,
/doyle-group-site/media/sroh/coolingsroh_hu_a255c50d4ef07120.webp 760w,
/doyle-group-site/media/sroh/coolingsroh_hu_330524dff36db1c0.webp 1200w"
src="https://avikar.net/doyle-group-site/media/sroh/coolingsroh_hu_a565ac579b4cf016.webp"
width="760"
height="198"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SrOH molecules were the first polyatomic molecules to be laser cooled, opening up the prospect of full quantum control over their internal states and trapping for long observation times [3]. There exists a pair of vibrational states in SrOH, namely a triply-excited bending vibration and a doubly-excited stretching vibration, with nearly the same energy but signicantly different dependences on μ. We have analyzed these states theoretically and found that a transition between them can be driven by microwave radiation, and their energy difference thereby directly measured [4]. Microwave-scale energies are more straightforwardly measured to high precision (e.g., compared to an optical-energy measurement using a frequency comb), and the small scale of the energy difference between the states suppresses potential systematic errors. We have also identied sets of rotational states in the two vibrational manifolds that are expected to have nearly-zero common-mode sensitivity to electric and magnetic fields, leading to strong suppression of common systematic errors associated with imperfect control of electromagnetic elds. With one day of integration, we expect an absolute microwave frequency sensitivity of about 3 μHz for oscillation frequencies between about 10 μHz (bounded from below by the full one-day duration of the measurement) and 1 Hz (bounded from above by the coherence time of the vibrational states).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This range of oscillation frequencies allows us to probe dark matter particles with masses between 1×10−20 and 4×10−15 eV/c2, which is a range of signicant theoretical interest in cosmological particle physics. With this sensitivity, we expect to probe new parameter space on beyond-the-Standard-Model particles such as dilatons (see right) to either rule out signicant parameter-space of such theories or discover the microscopic nature of dark matter.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[1] Katherine Garrett, Gintaras Duda, &amp;ldquo;Dark Matter: A Primer&amp;rdquo;, Advances in Astronomy, vol. 2011, Article ID 968283, 22 pages, 2011. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1155/2011/968283" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1155/2011/968283&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] M. S. Safronova, D. Budker, D. DeMille, D. F. Jackson Kimball, A. Derevianko, C. W. Clark, &amp;ldquo;Searches for new physics with atoms and molecules,&amp;rdquo; Rev. Mod. Phys. 90 (2018). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/RevModPhys.90.025008" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1103/RevModPhys.90.025008&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[3] I. Kozyryev, L. Baum, K. Matsuda, B. L. Augenbraun, L. Anderegg, A. P. Sedlack, and J. M. Doyle, &amp;ldquo;Sisyphus Laser Cooling of a Polyatomic Molecule&amp;rdquo; Phys. Rev. Lett. 118, 173201 (2017). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.118.173201" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.118.173201&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[4] I. Kozyryev, Z. D. Lasner, and J. M. Doyle, &amp;ldquo;Enhanced Sensitivity to Ultralight Bosonic Dark Matter in the Spectra of the Linear Radical SrOH,&amp;rdquo; arXiv:1805.08185&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>